Burlingame Family Papers
Burlingame Family Papers
- Organization records
  - U.S. Army
    - Miscellaneous, 1912-1944 (Box 27)
    - Certificates, 1918-1922 (Box 27)
    - Itineraries, 1942 (Box 27)
    - Lists, 1919-1946 (Box 27)
    - Photographs, 1914-1918; 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Photographs, 1918; 1940-1945; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Special orders and memoranda, 1917-1945 (Box 28)
- Writings
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1951 (Box 28)
  - Burlingame, Ann Whinton (Ann Watkins)
    - Article, "Literature for Sale", 1941 (Box 28)
    - Common Place Book, 1891-1897 (Box 28)
    - Speech, "Bowker Memorial Lecture", 1941 (Box 28)
  - Burlingame, Anson
    - Speech, Defense of Massachusetts, 1856 (Box 28)
  - Burlingame, Roger
    - Articles
      - "After The Crash", undated (Box 28)
      - "The Age of Paper", 1950; drafts; notes and research material (Box 28)
      - "All Out and After", undated (Box 28)
      - "American Christmas", undated; draft (Box 28)
      - "The American Way", undated (Box 28)
      - "America's First Evangelist of Science", 1947; Popular Science printed material (Box 28)
      - "The Analyst's Couch and the Creative Mind", 1959; draft; Harper's Magazine printed material (Box 28)
      - "Around the Corner", undated (Box 28)
      - "Art For Artists' Sake", undated (Box 28)
      - "Bottlenecks of Invention", 1951; draft; Nation's Business printed material (Box 28)
      - "The Best Tourist", undated (Box 28)
      - "Caesar's Ghost", undated (Box 28)
      - "The Century Club 1847-1947" (Box 28)
      - "Change and Decay on Capitol Hill", undated (Box 28)
      - "Chemurgy, A Strong New Weapon", 1941; Popular Science printed material (Box 28)
      - "The Cinzano Italy", undated (Box 28)
      - "The College Nobody Knows", undated (Box 28)
      - "Cooper Union, The Poor Man's College", 1950; 1959; draft; photographs; The American Mercury printed material (Box 29)
      - "Damn the Bonus", 1935; Today printed material (Box 29)
      - "Defense Material From the Farms", 1941 (Box 29)
      - "Do Not Feed or Annoy the Authors", undated (Box 29)
      - "Don't Be Your Own Architect", 1939; printed material (Box 29)
      - "Duchess", undated (Box 29)
      - "The Educational Exercise", undated (Box 29)
      - "Eli Whitney's Second Invention", 1938; Scribner's printed material (Box 29)
      - "Embattled Veterans", 1933; notes, research material, Atlantic Monthly printed material (Box 29)
      - "The End of the Summer", undated (Box 29)
      - "The English Machine", undated (Box 29)
      - "Escape", undated (Box 29)
      - "Evolution of Editors", 1949; New York Times Book Review printed material (Box 29)
      - "Experience of Becoming", undated (Box 29)
      - on Firearms, undated (Box 29)
      - "The First American", undated (Box 29)
      - "FM Radio Joins the Army", 1942; Popular Science printed material (Box 29)
      - "Forgetting", undated (Box 29)
      - "Franklin and the American Culture", undated (Box 29)
      - "Fred Taylor's Revolution", undated; draft; notes and outlines (Box 29)
      - "Freedom", undated (Box 29)
      - "Freedom and the Lone Wolf", undated (Box 29)
      - "From Barnstorming to Bombers", 1941; miscellaneous; notes, fragments; Popular Science printed material (Box 29)
      - "Gipsy, Come Away", undated (Box 29)
      - "Good Times for Authors", undated (Box 29)
      - "Gothenburg, Sweden", undated (Box 29)
      - "The 'Great' Frenchman", undated; Scribner's printed material (Box 29)
      - "The Hardware of Culture", 1959; drafts; printed material (Box 29)
      - "The Harvard World of Roger Burlingame", 1960; Harvard Alumni Bulletin printed material (Box 29)
      - "Heroes of the Telegraph", undated (Box 30)
      - "His Customers Were Right", 1951; Nation's Business printed material (Box 30)
      - "If You Weren't Educated", 1959; Think printed material (Box 30)
      - "I Have Known Many Worlds", 1959; Saturday Review printed material (Box 30)
      - "The Impossible Next War", 1936 (Box 30)
      - "Industrial Revolution", undated (Box 30)
      - "The Industrial Strikes", undated (Box 30)
      - "Intuition", undated (Box 30)
      - "In the Valley of Virginia", 1951; Atlantic Monthly printed material (Box 30)
      - "Is Abstract Art a Private Joke?", undated (Box 30)
      - "I Wanted Wings", 1944; 1945; draft; notes and research material (Box 30)
      - "John Marquand", 1937-1961; undated; draft; notes and research material (Box 30)
      - "John Wanamaker", undated (Box 30)
      - "Keep Watching Those Lumps", undated (Box 30)
      - "The Last Move", undated (Box 30)
      - "Law Breaking - British School", undated (Box 30)
      - "Letter to a Friend in re. the Communist Menace", undated (Box 30)
      - "Let Us Act Our Age", 1940; printed material (Box 30)
      - "Little Italy in Boston", circa 1912 (Box 30)
      - "Locarno, 1925", The Independent printed material (Box 30)
      - "Locomotives, Railways and Steamships", 1967; printed material (Box 30)
      - "Lost Records", undated (Box 30)
      - "Love Lyric", 1927; Life printed material (Box 30)
      - "Man Versus Gadget", undated (Box 30)
      - "Men, Tools, and Machines", 1941; Survey Graphic printed material (Box 30)
      - "Motives", undated (Box 30)
      - "Mountains of Paper", 1950; Harper's printed material (Box 30)
      - "Not at His Desk", undated (Box 31)
      - "The Oldest Challenge", undated (Box 31)
      - "The Olive Branch Petition", 1959 (Box 31)
      - "On to the Treasury", undated (Box 31)
      - " 'Peace, Hold Your Peace' ", undated (Box 31)
      - "The People Have a Plan", circa 1941; draft; notes and research material; McCall's printed material (Box 31)
      - "The People, Yes", undated (Box 31)
      - "Popular Science Pioneer", undated (Box 31)
      - "Power Anonymous", 1950; Reporter printed material (Box 31)
      - "Profit By My Experience", undated (Box 31)
      - "The Public Be Damned", undated (Box 31)
      - "Pulling Hats Out of Rabbits", 1941; Popular Science printed material (Box 31)
      - "Rainbow Over the Farm", 1937; 1939; draft; Harper's printed material (Box 31)
      - "The Rifle that Won the Revolution", 1938; The Marine Corps Gazette printed material; Scribner's printed material (Box 31)
      - "Roosevelt is Dead", undated (Box 31)
      - "Rugged is Right", undated (Box 31)
      - "Save the Saugatuck", undated (Box 32)
      - "Scribner Family", undated (Box 32)
      - "Sellers' Market in the Sticks", undated (Box 32)
      - "The Sixties: Coming Up in Technology", 1960; draft; Saturday Review printed material (Box 32)
      - "Socialized Medicine", undated (Box 32)
      - "The Sport of Writing", 1936; draft; Harper's printed material (Box 32)
      - "Stories By Rudyard Kipling", undated; book foreword (Box 32)
      - "Sunrise to Sunset", 1950; printed material Saturday Review of Literature (Box 32)
      - "Technology in the Sixties", circa 1960 (Box 32)
      - "Telepathy? or Just Plain Luck?", 1961 (Box 32)
      - "These Truths", undated (Box 32)
      - "They Got Together", undated (Box 32)
      - "They Who Edit Books", undated (Box 32)
      - "They Wore the Uniform", undated (Box 32)
      - "Through Change and Through Storm", undated (Box 32)
      - "Tired Radicals", undated (Box 32)
      - "The Train at Ligny", undated (Box 32)
      - "The 1960's: Trial and Error Decade", circa 1960 (Box 32)
      - "Twenty-Five Hours a Day", undated (Box 32)
      - "The Two-Way Street", 1959 (Box 32)
      - "The Unemployed", undated (Box 32)
      - "War Makes Thieves:' Peace Hangs Them", 1957; draft; American Heritage printed material (Box 32)
      - on: War vs. Isolationism, circa 1939 (Box 32)
      - "What is Art", undated (Box 32)
      - "Whittling Boy: The Story of Eli Whitney", 1941; The Commonweal printed material (Box 32)
      - "Wings", undated (Box 32)
      - "The Women of Our City", 1913 (Box 32)
    - Books
      - Album of American Industry
        - Outline, undated (Box 32)
      - The American Conscience
        - Blurb, circa 1957 (Box 32)
        - Drafts A-B, circa 1957; 4 folders (Box 33)
        - Fragments, circa 1957 (Box 33)
        - Introduction, circa 1957 (Box 33)
        - Note cards, circa 1957 (Box 33)
        - Notes, circa 1957 (Box 33)
        - Notes, circa 1957 (Box 34)
        - Outlines, circa 1957; 2 folders (Box 34)
      - The American Invention Myth
        - Outlines, undated (Box 34)
      - American Pioneers in Science
        - Notes and research material, undated (Box 34)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 34)
        - "Profiles" - Maj. Armstrong, undated (Box 34)
      - Backgrounds of Power
        - Draft fragments, circa 1949 (Box 34)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1949; 2 folders (Box 34)
        - Outlines (Box 34)
        - Reviews, circa 1949; 2 folders (Box 34)
      - Benjamin Franklin: Envoy Extraordinary
        - Draft A, circa 1955; 2 folders (Box 34)
        - Drafts B-F, circa 1955; 6 folders (Box 35)
        - Galley proofs, circa 1955; 3 folders (Box 36)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1955; 3 folders (Box 36)
        - Outlines, circa 1955; 4 folders (Box 36)
      - Cartwheels
        - Reviews, circa 1935 (Box 36)
      - The Consent of the Governed
        - Draft fragments, undated (Box 36)
        - Notes and research material, undated (Box 36)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 36)
      - Dictator Clock: 5000 Years of Telling Time
        - Draft fragments, circa 1966 (Box 37)
        - Drafts A-C, circa 1966; 3 folders (Box 37)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1966; 3 folders (Box 37)
        - Outlines, circa 1966; 3 folders (Box 37)
        - Unbound printed copy, circa 1966 (Box 37)
      - Don't Let Them Scare You
        - Draft fragments, circa 1961 (Box 37)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1961 (Box 37)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1961; 4 folders (Box 38)
        - Reviews, circa 1961 (Box 38)
      - The Easy Chair
        - Outlines, undated (Box 38)
      - Engines of Democracy
        - Notes and research material, circa 1940; 2 folders (Box 38)
        - Reviews, circa 1940 (Box 38)
      - General Billy Mitchell
        - Notes and research material, circa 1956 (Box 38)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1956 (Box 39)
        - Outlines, circa 1956 (Box 39)
      - Glass Industry
        - Notes and research material, undated; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Henry Ford
        - Galley proofs, circa 1955 (Box 39)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1955 (Box 39)
        - Outlines, circa 1955 (Box 39)
        - Reviews, circa 1955 (Box 39)
      - History of Invention
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 39)
      - The History of Technology
        - Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 39)
        - Draft fragments, 1966 (Box 39)
      - I Am a City Slicker
        - Drafts A-B, undated; 3 folders (Box 39)
        - Notes and research material, undated (Box 39)
        - Outlines, undated; 2 folders (Box 40)
      - I Have Known Many Worlds
        - Draft A, circa 1959; 2 folders (Box 40)
        - Galley proofs, 1959 (Box 40)
        - Reviews, 1959 (Box 40)
      - I Have Known Two Minds
        - Draft fragments, undated (Box 40)
        - Drafts A-B, undated; 4 folders (Box 40)
        - Drafts B-E, undated; 6 folders (Box 41)
      - Machines That Built America
        - Notes and research material, circa 1953 (Box 41)
      - The Making of Many Books
        - Miscellaneous, 1946; 2 folders (Box 41)
      - March of the Iron Men
        - Notes and research material, circa 1938 (Box 41)
        - Reviews, 1938-1941; 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Mosquitos in the Big Ditch, undated (Box 42)
      - Out of Silence into Sound: The Life of Alexander Graham Bell
        - Drafts A-D, circa 1964; 4 folders (Box 42)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1964; 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Patent Medicine
        - Notes and research material, 1951 (Box 42)
      - Peace Veterans
        - Notes and research material, 1932 (Box 42)
      - Scientists Behind the Inventions
        - Memos, 1957-1960 (Box 42)
        - Notes and research material, 1958 (Box 42)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 42)
      - The Sixth Column
        - Miscellaneous, 1963-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 42)
        - Miscellaneous, 1961-1965; 2 folders (Box 43)
        - Drafts A-E, circa 1962; 7 folders (Box 43)
        - Draft E, circa 1962 (Box 44)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1962 (Box 44)
        - Publicity, circa 1962 (Box 44)
      - The Social Effects of Machine Production
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 44)
      - The Social History of Machine Production
        - Drafts A-B, 1954-1955; 3 folders (Box 44)
        - Notes and research material, 1954-1955; 3 folders (Box 44)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 45)
      - The Story of McGraw-Hill
        - Miscellaneous, 1955-1960 (Box 45)
        - Draft A, undated; 3 folders (Box 45)
        - Galley Proofs, 1958 (Box 45)
      - Susan Shane
        - Reviews, circa 1926 (Box 46)
      - Thomas Alva Edison
        - Notes and research material, 1949 (Box 46)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 46)
      - Three Bags Full
        - Miscellaneous, 1936 (Box 46)
        - Drafts A-B, 1936; 4 folders (Box 46)
        - Drafts B-C, circa 1936; 7 folders (Box 47)
        - Draft D, circa 1936; 2 folders (Box 48)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1936; 2 folders (Box 48)
        - Reviews, 1936 (Box 48)
      - A Time To Hate
        - Draft fragments, undated (Box 48)
        - Drafts A-C, undated; 3 folders (Box 48)
        - Draft D, undated (Box 49)
      - Tom Paine
        - Outlines, undated (Box 49)
      - The Truth in the Dream
        - Introduction, undated (Box 49)
        - Notes and research material, undated (Box 49)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 49)
      - Victory Without Peace
        - Notes and research material, 1943-1944; 2 folders (Box 49)
      - What Next
        - Drafts, undated (Box 49)
      - Whittling Boy
        - Draft of foreword, circa 1941 (Box 49)
        - Draft of prologue, circa 1941 (Box 49)
        - Drafts A-B, circa 1941; 3 folders (Box 49)
        - Notes and research material, circa 1941; 2 folders (Box 50)
        - Reviews, circa 1941; 2 folders (Box 50)
        - Synopsis, circa 1941 (Box 50)
      - Who Really Invented the Steamship
        - Drafts A-B, undated; 2 folders (Box 50)
        - Notes and research material, undated (Box 50)
      - A Wild Surmise
        - Draft A, undated (Box 50)
        - Notes and research material, undated; 2 folders (Box 50)
        - Outlines, undated (Box 50)
      - You Too
        - Reviews, 1924 (Box 51)
    - Book reviews
      - "Again the Iron Horse", 1940; printed material, The Saturday Review (Box 51)
      - "Barrett Wendell and His Letters", 1924; printed material (Box 51)
      - "Cradle of Ships", undated (Box 51)
      - "Edison", undated (Box 51)
      - "Everyday Things in American Life", undated (Box 51)
      - "Expansion and Change", 1957 (Box 51)
      - "Fifty Years of Popular Mechanics, 1902-1952", 1951; printed material, Herald Tribune book review (Box 51)
      - "Ford: The Times, the Man, and the Company", undated (Box 51)
      - "From Trail Dust to Star Dust", undated (Box 51)
      - "The Gingerbread Age", undated (Box 51)
      - "The Golden Age", circa 1912 (Box 51)
      - "Highball: A Pageant of Trains", undated (Box 51)
      - "A History of the Colt Revolver and Other Arms...from 1836-1940", undated (Box 51)
      - "Man the Maker: A History of Technology and Engineering", 1951; drafts; printed material, Herald Tribune book review (Box 51)
      - "Iron Horses: American Locomotives 1829-1900", undated (Box 51)
      - "Kindling", undated (Box 51)
      - "Made in America", undated (Box 51)
      - "Mechanization Takes Command", undated (Box 51)
      - "An Outline of Man's Knowledge of the Modern World", 1960; printed material, New York Times book review (Box 51)
      - "Pioneer of the. Age of Power", undated (Box 51)
      - "Steelways of New England", undated (Box 51)
      - "Sunrise to Sunset", undated (Box 51)
    - Diaries, 1916-1943; undated; 4 folders (Box 51)
    - Poetry
      - "Interval", undated; printed material (Box 51)
      - "To Ruth and Virgil on Their Fiftieth", 1963 (Box 51)
      - "The Women Will Soon Knit Again", 1940; printed material, New York Times Magazine (Box 51)
      - Untitled, 1895-1903; undated; 3 folders (Box 51)
      - Untitled, 1910-1936; 3 folders (Box 52)
    - Radio scripts
      - "American Scriptures", undated (Box 52)
      - "American Story", undated (Box 52)
    - Research materials
      - Index cards and notebooks, 1940-1951 (Box 56, 57)
    - Short stories
      - "Bachelors on Horseback", undated; printed material (Box 52)
      - "Birthday", undated (Box 52)
      - "Black Masquers at Thanksgiving", undated (Box 52)
      - "Carnations", 1933; printed material (Box 52)
      - "Caveat", undated (Box 52)
      - "The Celebration", undated (Box 52)
      - "The Children", 1932; printed material (Box 52)
      - "City Folks", undated (Box 52)
      - "Death Wish" or "Twenty Feet of Rope", undated; drafts A-B; 2 folders (Box 52)
      - "Dinner at Vatel", undated; drafts A-B; 2 folders (Box 52)
      - "The Eternal Youth", undated (Box 52)
      - "Everything Is All Right", undated (Box 52)
      - "The Fling", 1937; printed material, Redbook (Box 52)
      - "First Experiences at a Stage Door", circa 1912 (Box 52)
      - "Gallegher's Break", 1949 (Box 52)
      - "Grappa", undated (Box 52)
      - "The Heir", circa 1929 (Box 52)
      - "The Hen That Crossed the Road", undated (Box 52)
      - "Honey Bones", 1933; printed material, Sunday News (Box 52)
      - "The Hottest Battle", 1936; draft A; printed material, Sunday News (Box 52)
      - "The House in Crawford Notch", circa 1912 (Box 52)
      - "Incident", 1929; printed material (Box 52)
      - "It's Going To Be Different", undated (Box 52)
      - "Jacinth", undated; pr. mat (Box 52)
      - "The Last Equation", 1936; draft A; printed material, Story Magazine (Box 52)
      - "Leave Before Sailing", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Machine from Rome", undated (Box 53)
      - "Manhattan Love", undated (Box 53)
      - "Milo's Business", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Miracle Draft", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Monkey Wrench", undated (Box 53)
      - "The New Intern", undated; printed material (Box 53)
      - "Obligato", undated (Box 53)
      - "Old Master", circa 1905; undated; drafts A-B; printed material, Cosmopolitan (Box 53)
      - "Only Seventeen", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Poker Game", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Road from Rome", undated (Box 53)
      - "Singing in the Rain", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Sixth Reel", undated (Box 53)
      - "Snake", 1925 (Box 53)
      - "The Sorrowful City", 1933; printed material (Box 53)
      - "Third Year", undated; printed material (Box 53)
      - "Three Days in Delirium", circa 1912 (Box 53)
      - "Watch Ticks", undated (Box 53)
      - "When the Corn Was Cut", undated (Box 53)
      - "When the Door Shut", 1935; printed material (Box 53)
      - "Yellow Roses", undated; printed material (Box 53)
      - "Young Love", undated (Box 53)
      - Untitled, circa 1912 (Box 53)
    - Speeches
      - "Appreciation of Contemporary Literature", undated (Box 53)
      - "Meeting Kipling" undated, 1847 (Box 53)
      - "Saugatuck Valley Association", undated (Box 53)
      - "The Social History of Machine Production", 1854-1955 (Box 53)
      - "Sources of Creative Writing", 1949-1950 (Box 53)
      - "Technology: Neglected Clue to Historical Change", undated (Box 53)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 53)
    - Untitled
      - Ideas, undated (Box 54)
      - on: Technology, undated (Box 54)
  - Burlingame, Walter A.
    - "Peking", 1867 (Box 54)
- Miscellany
  - Articles
    - Biggerstaff, Knight / "A Translation of Anson Burlingame's Instructions...", circa 1936 (Box 54)
    - Bolton, Theodore / "Charles Loring Elliott", 1942 (Box 54)
    - Fairfax, Downey / "Mark Lescarbot Writes a Ballade...", undated (Box 54)
    - Frankfurter, Felix / "Charles Culp Burlingham", 1960; 1977 Accession (Box 54)
    - Galantiere, Lewis / "America Today: A Freehand Society", 1950; 1977 Accession (Box 54)
    - Green, Elizabeth and Handy, Craighill / " 'Mei-kuo' First", 1943 (Box 54)
    - Jones, Bassett / "Arithmetic Monsters and Economic Absurdities"; "The Modern Pythagoras"; Letter to Editor, 1942-1959 (Box 54)
    - Jones, Bassett / "A Letter to a Banker", undated (Box 54)
    - Mitman, Carl W. / "Stevens's 'Porcupine' Boiler, 1804: A Recent Study", 1939; 1977 Accession (Box 54)
    - Painton, Fred / "Here Comes Gabriel", circa 1944 (Box 54)
    - Painton, Fred / "Lord Pity the Censor", undated (Box 54)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur M. / "Political Mobs and the American Revolution, 1765-1776", 1955; 1977 Accession (Box 54)
    - Sizer, Theodore / "The Story of the Edwards Portrait", 1959; 1977 Accession (Box 54)
    - Thomas, Norman / "The Socialist Cure for a Sick Society", 1932 (Box 54)
    - White, Lynn / "Technology and Invention in the Middle Ages", 1940 (Box 54)
    - Whiton, Barbara / "The Influence of France on America", 1965 (Box 54)
  - Books
    - Author unknown / "The Henry Ford Nobody Knows", undated (Box 54)
    - MacArthur, Turner K. / "Between You and Me and Adolph Hitler", undated (Box 55)
    - Streeter, Edward / "Window on America", 1959 (Box 55)
  - Collected works
    - Goodman, Nathan G., circa 1937-1938 (Box 55)
    - Lundbergh, Holger, undated (Box 55)
    - Wharton, Edith, undated (Box 55)
  - Drawings
    - Summer Pool by H.D. (ink on paper), 7 Jul 1946 (Oversize 6)
    - Cathedral of St. John the Divine by Walter Tittle (ink on paper), undated (Oversize 6)
  - Verse
    - Bacon, Leonard / Miscellaneous, 1945-1951 (Box 55)
    - Burt, Struthers / "Resurgem", 1927 (Box 55)
    - Collins, Kathleen / Untitled, 1950-1961 (Box 55)
    - Keller, Georgena / Untitled, 1929-1958 (Box 55)
    - Laing, Alexander / "Poems for a New Year in a New Age", 1946 (Box 55)
    - Laing, Dilys Bennett / "Not One Atoll"; "Incorrupt" (Box 55)
    - McKinney, Laurence / "Golden Almanac", undated (Box 55)
  - Short stories
    - Ainsworth, Henry / "The Man Who Saw", circa 1908 (Box 55)
    - Ross, Gavin / "Sixty Words a Minute", undated (Box 55)
  - Speeches
    - Cowdin, Elliot C. / "Tribute to the Memory of Anson Burlingame", 1870 (Box 55)
    - Franckenstein, Kay Boyle / on Joseph M. Franckenstein, 1964 (Box 55)
    - Wicks, William P. / on Medicine, 1951 (Box 55)